Inventory of the Ladislav Feierabend Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ladislav Feierabend papers,
1922-1975
78058
Feierabend, Ladislav, 1891-1969
21 manuscript boxes (8.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoirs, photographs, and printed matter, relating to agricultural administration, Czechoslovakia in World War II, and Czechoslovak foreign relations with Germany and the Soviet Union.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
Czechoslovak agricultural economist; minister of agriculture, 1938-1940; minister of finance, Czechoslovak government-in-exile (London), 1941-1945.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence, speeches and writings, memoirs, photographs, and printed matter, relating to agricultural administration, Czechoslovakia in World War II, and Czechoslovak foreign relations with Germany and the Soviet Union.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Agriculture.; Czechs--United States.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--Germany.; Czechoslovakia--Foreign relations--Soviet Union.; Czechoslovakia--History--1938-1945.; Germany.; Germany--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Foreign relations--Czechoslovakia.; United States.
Occupations
Statesmen--Czechoslovakia.
Container List
- Articles, documents (Box 1-2)
  - 1955-1975 (First Republic) (Folder 1: 1-3)
  - 1948-1970 (articles re Munich, London 1938-1945, Dr. E Beneš, Otázka česko-slovenská; documents referring to 1939-1941) (Folder 1: 4-5)
  - 1950-1965 (Protectorate, German occupation of Czechoslovakia, the resistance in Czechoslovakia). (Folder 1: 6-7)
    Includes postcards of Prague after May 1945
  - 1948-1968 (communist coup d'état, 1948; Prague Spring, 1968, J. Masaryk, M. Horáková, Gen. Hel. Pika) (Folder 2: 1)
  - 1968-1975 (Soviet invasion, 1968 August, Dr. Kriegl's speech, J. Palach, foreign affairs, Charter 1977). (Box-folder 2: 2)
    Includes reports from Prague and postcards of the 1968 events
- Articles and lectures by various Czech and Slovak politicians and scholars (Box 2-3)
  - 1950-1965 (politics, economics, agriculture). In Czech and Slovak. (Folder 2: 3-4)
  - Undated (politics and history). In Czech. (Folder 2: 5-6)
  - 1950-1959 (politics and agriculture). In English, French, German. (Folder 3: 1)
- Articles and lectures by various American, Czech, and Slovak politicians and scholars (politics, history, sciences). In English. (Folder 3: 2-5)
- Correspondence and documents (Box 3-4)
  - Rada Svobodného Československa (The Council of Free Czechoslovakia)
    - 1953 (Folder 3: 6)
    - 1949-1951 (Folder 4: 1-2)
    - 1952-1968 (Folder 4: 3-4)
  - Československá Společnost pro Védy a Uměni (S.V.U.), Czechoslovak Society of Arts and Sciences, 1958-1968 (Folder 4: 5)
- Articles, 1968-1969 (Soviet economy and politics) (Folder 4: 6)
- Correspondence (Box 5)
  - 1964 (letters to Ladislav Feierabend from Ing. J. Martinásek and Ing. K. Staller, on Bren Comp. Ltd., Great Britain, 1941-1948, and armament affair, London, 1941-1942; complements to Political Memoirs, vols. IV-V (in Czech), vols. I-II (in German) (Folder 5: 1-2)
  - Letters to M. Sigmund and other documents referring to Bren Comp. Ltd. and armament affair, London, 1941-1942; complements to Political Memoirs, vols. IV-V (Folder 5: 3)
  - 1957-1964 (comments from politicians, participants, etc. on years 1941-1943; complements to Political Memoirs, vols. I-V) (Folder 5: 4)
  - 1968-1969 (comments from politicians and others on years 1945-1948; complements to Political Memoirs, vol. VIII) (Folder 5: 5)
  - Comments and complements by Dr. Juraj Slavik to Political Memoirs, vols. I-II and IV-IX, and by Dr. E. Táborský, Dr. M. Schubrt, D. Čipera, Dr. J. Němec, E. Koeppl, Dr. J. Citta, Šejnona, J. Hyka (Folder 5: 6)
- Study, "A Plan for the Reform of Land Tenure in Middle Europe." Typescript. (Folder 5: 7-8)
- Photocopies (budgets of Czechoslovak Government-in-Exile, London, 1941-1943, explanations re budget for years 1942 and 1943 by Finance Minister Ladislav Feierabend) (Folder 6: 1)
- Copies of periodical Listy Přatelům (letters to friends), issued monthly by the British Group of the Czech Agrarian Party, Ladislav Feierabend editor, London, 1948-1950; articles by Ladislav Feierabend, M. Rašin, Č. Toren, J. Ševčik, and others; letters from members, Republikánská štrana čsl. zemědělskeho lidu v exilu, Paris and London, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 6: 2-3)
- Correspondence (Box 6-8)
  - 1948-1949 (J. Filipek, secretary to Ladislav Feierabend before World War II; P. Zenkl, M. Žemlička, Lustig, Hořák and others on agrarians in exile, politics, and private matters) (Folder 6: 4-5)
  - 1947-1949 (Dr. Mládek, Dr. E. Hexner, Dr. A. Basch, Dr. J. Opočenský, members of M. R., English, Czech, and American friends referring to Ladislav Feierabend searching for a position, politics, and private matters) (Folder 6: 6)
  - 1948-1949 (letters to Ladislav Feierabend from V. Brzorád, H. Ripkal, J. Stránský, J. Ševčik, Č. Torn, Tumliř, L. Prchala on politics and on Ladislav Feierabend searching for a position) (Folder 7: 1)
  - 1948-1949 (letters to Ladislav Feierabend from S. Ingr, Š. Kočvara, F. Némec, J. Papánek, M. Rechcigl, J. Slavik, V. Svoboda, J. Zeman, on politics) (Folder 7: 2-3)
  - 1948-1950 (letters to Ladislav Feierabend from V. Brdlik, Fr. Král, Ant. Pavel, Oldřich Škvor, Jiři Škvor, J. J. Štăstný, J. Voženilek, on politics). (Folder 7: 4)
    Includes a report about Czechoslovakia
  - 1948-1949 (letters to Ladislav Feierabend from K. Kesl and certain émigrés in Germany and Great Britain, on politics and personal matters (Box-folder 7: 5)
  - Letters to Ladislav Feierabend from D. Čipera, J. Bertl, Dr. Vl. Černý, Dr. J. Pluhař, Dr. M. Rašin, L. Sliva, certain Czech Rotarians, Czechosklovak Relief Committee, London, J. Josten, J.F.C.I., on politics and personal matters (Folder 7: 6)
- Reports of lecturing, memorandum, etc. re the activity of Ladislav Feierabend with Rada Svobodného Československa, 1950-1955, London, New York, Washington, D.C.; letters from Dr. V. Hlavatý (Folder 7: 7)
  - 1950-1952 (Mid-European Studies Center, New York, and State Department, on projects for agricultural studies) (Folder 8: 1-2)
  - 1952-1955 (Mid-European Studies Center, New York, and colleges, universities, and other institutions, on lectures in the United States and Canada re politics and economics) (Folder 8: 3-4)
- Articles and Czech lectures on politics, economics, and agriculture. Typescript and printed copies. (Box 8)
  - 1951-1967 (Folder 8: 5-6)
  - 1950-1954 (Folder 8: 7-8)
- Articles on agricultural policy, targets and politics, Košice program, agricultural plans, etc., 1955 (Folder 8: 8-9)
- Study on social legislation, 1952. In Czech. (Folder 9: 1)
- Clippings (reviews and polemics re Political Memoirs) (Box 9)
  - 1961-1963 (vols. I-III) (Folder 9: 2-3)
  - 1964-1969 (vols. IV-VIII) (Folder 9: 4)
- Correspondence (Box 9-10)
  - 1961-1965 (letters from readers, politicians, scholars, etc., with comments and complements to Political Memoirs, vols. I-II). (Folder 9: 5)
    Includes some letters from 1939
  - 1964-1966 (letters from readers, politicians, historians, with comments and complements to Political Memoirs, vols. III-IV) (Folder 9: 6)
  - 1966-1969 (letters from readers, politicians, and historians, with comments and complements to Political Memoirs, vols. V-VIII). (Folder 10: 1)
    Includes statement about Masaryk's death, 1948; Héidrich, J., "The Last Days of Jan Masaryk"
- Unpublished supplements to Political Memoirs (articles, letters, documents, photographs, 1940-1945) (Box 10)
  - 1956-1963 (Folder 10: 2)
  - 1956-1964. (Box-folder 10: 3)
    Includes photocopies of letters from President Beneš to Ladislav Feierabend re resignation on February 28, 1945; letters from the Chancellor of the Exchequer; book by Z. Fierlinger
- Correspondence, 1963-1969 (Box 10)
  - Letters from Ing. F. Satora, Ivan Herben (messages from Prague during World War II, and editing of the memoirs) (Folder 10: 4)
  - Letters from Památnik Nár. Pisemnietvi na Strahově, Praha; Miloš, Stádnik, Josef Paleček, Dr. Planner, Dr. O. Petrů, Dr. Rýpar, Dr. Fr. Schwarzenberg (editing and publishing of the memoirs; exhibition of books from exile, "Návraty" Naarden Committee; Czech clergymen in Rome) (Folder 10: 5)
- Copies of Dr. Jan Opočenský diary (Box 10-12)
  - Part I - 1940 July 2-October 30; 1941 January 1-February 28 (London) (Folder 10: 6-7)
  - Part I - 1941 March 1-December 31; 1942 January 1-November 5 (London) (Folder 11: 1-2)
  - Part I - 1942 November 6 - 1945 July (London); 1945 August 30-September 27 (Prague) (Folder 11: 3-4)
  - Part II - 1941 March 1-November 4; 1942 November 6-December 27 (London) (Folder 11: 5)
  - Part III - 1942 December 29 - 1943 December 28 (London) (Box-folder 11: 6-7)
  - Part IV - 1943 December 28 - 1944 September 10 (London) (Folder 12: 1)
  - Part V - 1944 September 11 - 1945 April 22 (London) (Folder 12: 2)
- Lectures on agriculture, economics, and politics, delivered in the United States at universities, colleges, and other institutions, 1950-1952 (Folder 12: 3)
- Articles and lectures on agriculture, economics, and politics (lectures delivered in the United States at universities, colleges, and other institutions) (Box 12-13)
  - 1953 (Folder 12: 4-5)
  - Undated (Folder 12: 6)
  - 1953-1964. (Folder 13: 1)
    Includes two articles, 1962 and 1964
- Letters and clippings on politics, and lectures delivered in Great Britain at different institutions, 1948-1950. In English and Czech (Folder 13: 2)
- Letters and lectures on politics, Free Masonary in Czechoslovakia, escape from Czechoslovakia (lectures delivered at various Rotary Clubs in Great Britain and the United States, and Masonic Lodges in the United States), 1948-1961 (Folder 13: 3)
- Personal broadcast typescript transcripts on politics, 1950-1955 (broadcast on Radio Free Europe and Voice of America). (Folder 13: 4-5)
- Broadcast transcripts on agriculture and economics (broadcast on Voice of America), 1960-1969.In Czech and English. (Folder 13: 6)
- Articles and obituaries of different Czechoslovak politicians, writers, and scholars (Box-folder 13: 7-8)
- Correspondence, 1961-1974 (K. Matzker - translator of memoirs into German, vols. I-IV; Ladislav Feierabend, Mrs. J. Feierabend, H. Kuhn, G. Rhode), translation of supplements unpublished in German, vols. I-IV (Folder 14: 1)
- Translation into German by K. Matzker, vol. III. Typescript and notes. (Folder 14: 2)
- Personal documents, 1948-1969 (private correspondence and articles by Ivo and Rosalina Feierabend) (Folder 14: 3-4)
- Lectures and articles by Jana Feierabend (Milada Horákova, Ravensbrück concentration camp, brief survey of Czechoslovak history, art in Czechoslovakia), 1952-1955 and 1960-1965 (Folder 14: 5-6)
- Miscellany (Folder 15: 1)
- "Kniha Druhá - Vyvrcholení Životni Činnosti Členem Československých Vlád v Osudových Dobach" (Box 15-19)
  - Vols. 1-3. (Folder 15: 2-7)
  - Vols. 4-6 (Folder 16: 1-8)
  - Vols. 7-9 (Folder 17: 1-7)
  - Vols. 10-12 (Folder 18: 1-6)
  - Vols. 13-14 (Folder 19: 1-4)
  - Materials (Folder 19: 5)
- TCM "Budu Se Na Vás Divat" (unidentified typescript) (Folder 20: 1-2)
- Study, 1952 (agricultural administration in free countries and in communist states). In English. (Folder 20: 3)
- Printed matter (Box 20-21)